<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the great antidote of Van Helmont, Paracelsus and Crollius ... called the elixir proprietatis known by all physicians to be the greatest cordial and onely medicine in the world for long and sound life ... / written by J.H., a lover of truth, and made publick for the good of all people.</title>
            <author>J. H., lover of truth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H82</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35446</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15305759</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15305759</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45621)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1189:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the great antidote of Van Helmont, Paracelsus and Crollius ... called the elixir proprietatis known by all physicians to be the greatest cordial and onely medicine in the world for long and sound life ... / written by J.H., a lover of truth, and made publick for the good of all people.</title>
                  <author>J. H., lover of truth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paracelsus, 1493-1541.</term>
               <term>Helmont, Jean Baptiste van, 1577-1644.</term>
               <term>Croll, Oswald, ca. 1560-1609.</term>
               <term>Therapeutics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103400:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF The GREAT ANTIDOTE of <hi>Van Helmont, Paracelſus</hi> and <hi>Crollius;</hi> By them called the Elixir Proprietatis: Known by all Phyſicians to be the greateſt Cordial and onely Medicine in the World for long and ſound Life, reſtoring Nature even at the point of Death, and effectually taking away the Seeds of all DISEASES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> An Examination of AUTHORS concerning its true Preparation: <hi>As alſo,</hi> A ready way to Volatile <hi>Salt of Tartar,</hi> by which this <hi>Elixir</hi> is truly prepared.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>J. H.</hi> a Lover of truth, and made publick for the good of all people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the AUTHOR. 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:103400:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103400:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have here ſhewed thee ſeveral ways to make the <hi>Elixir Proprietatis,</hi> by which thou mayeſt underſtand the difference betwixt a good and a bad; and for that end I have ſet down <hi>Crollius</hi> his way of prepareing it with Oyl of Sulphur,<note place="margin">To joyn a Mineral with a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitable, is an Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in Philoſophy.</note> which is that middle way that <hi>Van Helmont</hi> ſaith (being ſo made) it is of no worth. I have ſet down the ſayings of <hi>Van Helmont</hi> concerning Volatiſing Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> and its Virtues being Volatiſed, which is the only Solvent by which this Medicine is truly made: and for the virtues thereof, I am of <hi>Paracelſus</hi>'s mind, that the Age of a Man, is too little for the finding out of them: I have expreſt ſome few experiments, but could have done more, and more conſiderable, as healing the Leproſey, the Scroffulous humour commonly called the Evil, two ſorts of Gouts, the bringing forth the Mercury of thoſe that have been Salivated for the Venerial Diſeaſe: and many others, too tedious to mention. If thou art Ingenious thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt profit thereby. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Since the Fire, from my Houſe in</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Shadwell, <hi>betwixt the</hi> New Church <hi>and</hi> Ratcliff, <hi>at the Sign of</hi> John Baptiſta Van Helmont.</dateline>
               <signed>J. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103400:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn Baptiſta Van Helmont</hi> in the 457 pag. ſaith, he will ſpeak ſo far as the order of Charity will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, of the revealing of Arcanums or ſecrets in Medicines: Firſt of all, Nature hath by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, produced ſingular remedies in the vegetable Monarchy, whereby Diſeaſes are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly reſtored and cured, which hitherto for want of diligent ſearching, a covetous deſire and envy of the Devil, have remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hidden; for ſo the <hi>Elixir Proprietatis</hi> of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> cureth the Aſthmah, the Falling Sickneſs, Appoplexy, Palſey,<note n="*" place="margin">A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption for want of Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Atrophia, Tabes or Conſumption of the Lungs. And becauſe this <hi>Elixir</hi> is not prepared but by a Skilful Phyloſopher, who not by thinking but by knowing is perfectly and doublely choſen thereunto, and ſo hath obtained the Title of our Adeptiſt, therefore out of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, I will unfold a middle way: <hi>R.</hi> beſt Myrrh, bright Alloes, of the beſt Saffron, of each one Ounce, if thou take more thou ſhall find it done in vain; let the two firſt be beaten and the Saffron role it into a round figure, put them into a large glaſs with a long neck, and ſeal it Hermetically and digeſt them in a gentle heat, for fear of breaking the glaſs, untill you ſee the whole lump grow to the bottom of the glaſs, and a cleer oyl and water circulate in the ſides of the glaſs, then open the glaſs, and poure on a pinte of Cinnamon water, and diſtil it in moiſt ſand until no more will aſcend: with thfs Medicine, ſaith he, I have as well diſſolved Quartan-Agues as continual Feavers, ſo that he who over night had taken the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and received his <hi>Sacro Sanctum Viaticum,</hi> and the extreme Unction of Oyl, hath had me his gueſt by his Bed at dinner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paracelſus</hi> in his Archedoxes hath theſe words, <hi>R.</hi> Myrrh, Alloes, Saffron, of each a like quantity, put them in a Pelican cloſed for two Months in a ſand Furnace in a gentle heat: after put the matter in a Limbeck and diſtill over the oyl without burning, cicrulate this oyl for a month, and after keep it for uſe. He ſaith the virtues of all Balſams are contained in this Medicine, and that it doth keep back old Age, the moſt of any one Medicine, and that the life of a Man is two ſhort for the finding out its virtues.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103400:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Crollius</hi> in 250 <hi>page.</hi> writes thus thus, <hi>R.</hi> Myrrh, Alloes, Saffrou, of each four Ounces, powder them, and pour on them ſo much Alcalizate Spirit of Wine, as will reduce them into them form of paſte, then pour on ſo much Oyl of Sulphur made by a Bell ſtill as will colour them black, then pour on Spirit of Wine tartarized as will cover them four fingers over, put them in a glaſs in digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for two days, ſeperate the tincture, and pour on pure Spirit of Wine, circulate it two months, ſeperate the tincture and diſtill the fecis by a gentle heat.</p>
            <p>What comes over add to the tinctures, and it will be far better than the vulgar way diſtilled; for the virtues, he ſaith, it removes all obſtructions of the Lungs, and Cheſt Pipes, prevents popular Infection, and Infectious Airs, and Peſtilential Feavers, removes all peſtifferous humours in the Stomach and Bowels, and eaſes all pains there: Takes away all obſtructions of the Brain, curing the Virtigo, Megrim, and dimneſs of ſight, comforts the memory, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents the Palſey, and Gout, quickens the Intelects and all the ſenſes, breaks the Stone in the Reins or Bladder, comforts the Heart and exprells Melancholly, eaſes the <hi>Illiaco Paſſio,</hi> and dolour of the Ribs, carries away Salt humours inſenſibly, and all Surfeits from intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Diet or Drinking, cures the third day Ague, and Hectick Feaver, brings forth congealed blood, and ſpeedily heals all inward Ulcers and Wounds; and, ſaith he, all diſeaſes proceeding either from head or cold; are by this Medicine healed: now thus far he.</p>
            <p>My way of preparing of it is this: <hi>R.</hi> the beſt Myrrh, bright Alloes, of the beſt Engliſh Saffron, of each four ounces; beat the the Myrrh and Alloes but not the Saffron, put them into a Bolt-head, and pour on them a pint and a half of volatil Salt of Tartar, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latized with Spirit of Wine, diſgeſt them in a gentle heat, till the gummouſneſs be fully gone, and there remain no more bitterneſs then is contained in the Saffron; then ſeperate the pure Spirit from the fecis, and keep it for uſe. This <hi>Elixir</hi> thus prepared, will in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour reſemble the pure Arterial Blood of a ſound and healthy man; and in taſt will be fragrant, in which the Myrrh and Saffron, will plainly appear very ſtrong in taſt, without any offenſiveneſs or nauſeouſneſs, but grateful to the Stomach.</p>
            <p>Now that I may not tantalize the Reader, in mentioning the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of volatile Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> and not ſhewing the way to make it,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103400:4"/>therefore I ſhall expreſs it as far as it is lawful. Take of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>According to</hi> Ramund Lulley <hi>in his</hi> Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta Nova.</note> red <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar qs.</hi> calſine it till it be white, then diſſolve it in Spirit of Wine, twice its weight ſuch as will burn having Gunpowder in it, till if fire the powder, and continue feeding it three months, untill the Salt and Spirit ſublime together, then ſeperate his Flegm, and keep it for uſe; this is that Solvent which I prepare this <hi>Elixir</hi> with and which <hi>Van Helmont</hi> in his Treatiſe of Feavers, 780 <hi>page. Quod ſi autem ad ſtud ignis arcanum, non pertingatis diſcite ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em</hi> Tartari <hi>reddere volatilem, ut hujus medio veſtras diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutiones perfeciatas qui etſi ſua ſoluta anatice homogenia deſerat digeſtus in nobis: illorum tamen aliquot vires mutuatus eſt quas intrò deſert plurimorum morborum domiarices.</hi> Which ſounds thus in <hi>Engliſh:</hi> If you cannot attain to that<note n="*" place="margin">His great Solvent called the Alkaheſt.</note> hidden Fire at leaſt learn to make the Salt of <hi>Tartar</hi> volatile, that by it you may make your diſſolutions of Bodies, which being truly homogenial and although digeſted in us, yet it hath borrowed the virtues of the diſſolved matter, which it contains to our principles as the ſubduer of moſt Diſeaſes. And in 787 <hi>page. Sufficit mihi quod ille Spiritus alcali ad hiſce Corporibus in ſalem redactus volatilem &amp; coagulabilem in officinia ſtomachi ad nermam ciborum redactus tranſeat in meſaraicas ſaltem per lotium iſt hac deportatus &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eundo lambat reſolvatque ſordes ibidem ſubnatas vi exotica ſibi aſſumpta,</hi> ſaith he, it is ſufficient for me that Salt of <hi>Tartar</hi> vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and reduced in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hop of the Stomach, unto the form of meats, paſſeth into the Meſeraick Veins, or being conveyd thether by the Urine doth clenſe all obnoxious humours there congealed, though they never ſo obſtinately adhere to the Veſſels.</p>
            <p>And in the 802 <hi>page. Naturam eſſe morbeum medicatricem eam Confortandam ideo non Conſternandam.</hi> Nature being the Phyſicianeſs of Diſeaſes ſhe is to be Stengthened and Comforted, and not hurt or hindre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Si enim ſordes primis adhaeſerent latebris inſiſtendum reſolutivis &amp; abſterſivis natura tuto ſatagente reliquum: ſui vero penetiori receſſu aliquid pertinacius occultiuſque reſtiterit aſſumenda ſunt alcalia volatilia que inſtar ſaponis cuncta abſtergunt.</hi> Saith he, if foulneſs ſhall adhere to the firſt veſſels, we may uſe clenſing Medicines, Nature ſafely doing the reſt; but if ſtubborn obſtructions ſhall ſecretly lodge in a more inward part, then volatile alcalies are to be made uſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103400:4"/>of, which waſh away the cauſes of all Diſeaſes, as Soap waſhes Linnen: And in the ſame <hi>page,</hi> he ſaith, Its a wonder how much the Salt of <hi>Tartar</hi> will perform, for it ſcours all dreggiſhneſs of obſtructing Filths out of the Veins, and all collections of Apoſthums; and ſaith he, being made volatile with Spirit of Wine, and not Oyl, is made good the ſaying of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> that where ever this Spirit will not reach, ſcarce any other pirit more powerfully ſhall come; this is part of the praiſe that <hi>Van Helmont</hi> and <hi>Paracelſus</hi> give of the volatile Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> which is the Spirit by which this medicine is made by adding only Myrrh, Alloes, Saffron, which Mr. <hi>Woodall</hi> in his <hi>Chyrurgeons Mate,</hi> affirms that by theſe three ingredients without any preparation, he hath cured the Tokens. Now if this Spirit be ſo Noble, and enriched by theſe ingredients for this Liquor by the help of the fire clenſes that is foul, digeſts that is vitulent, and inverts its malignity, and by means thereof is the virtue exalted and made more Noble by a thouſand fold: So that wee have here a Spirit not corroſive but familliar to the vegital nature, the moſt Noble of all Dulcified Salts made Ballamical, and of a ſeminal virtue, by its own Spirit, by which the three ſpecies, <hi>viz.</hi> Myrrh, Alloes, Saffron, are opened volatized, and made Spiritual, ſo that beſides the Fragrant Spirit, there is alſo the ſubſtantial tincture, and all joyned which ſuch a Salt that is friendly to nature, which by reaſon of its alcalizate nature, it is marvelous abſterſive, reſolving all muceous foulneſs, cutting and attenuating all tough Flegmatick coaggulations which it finds in its paſſage, bringing them forth part by Urin and Sweat, and ſometimes Siege.</p>
            <p>This Medicine thus prepared, is that which I have had experience of for ſome years, for which I owe eternal thanks and praiſe to Almighty God: for had I not had this, (though I have many others by which I have performed many excellent cures) yet for all them, I had not been here to have writ this, for in the height of the Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1665, I was taken with a Lethargy with that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that for the ſpace of ſeven days I could take nothing but drink, my drink was ſometimes Sack, and ſometimes Ale; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I was ſenſeleſs for many hours together, and when I recovered my ſenſes a little, I did ſtill call for and took this Medicine, and by Gods bleſſing on it, was perfectly cured, though it was reported with much confidence, that I was both dead and buried, and by no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103400:5"/>inconſiderable perſons neither, and at the ſame time all my Family was moſt dangerous Ill, my Son, a Child of eight years old, was taken with an Impoſtumation in his Neck near the jugular Vein, which Diſtemper he had two years before in the ſame place, when formerly coming out of the Country, was taken with it the next day, and now by reaſon of my illneſs, I could not ſo mind it, but that it came to a ſupputation, and I being a little recovered, was much troubled to ſee, but in ſhort time brought forth the matter and healed it, and ſince he hath continued well. My daughter of the age of ten, had a Blane on her Breaſt, but did not keep the houſe four days for it. May wife had a Peſtelential Feaver, but was cured of it in three or four days, though in the beginning of the Feaver, by taking this Medicine, there came forth many Feaver Spots, and the Nurſes ſeeing them, did conclude ſhe had the <hi>Tokens,</hi> and it was talked publikely abroad, that I had cured her of the <hi>Tokens,</hi> which thing I abſolutely deny to be within the reach of any Mortal Man to cure the real <hi>Tokens,</hi> though there are many ſorts of Spots not much unlike, which are as eaſily cured as the Diſeaſe they proceed from, as Surfeit Spots, Purple Scurvy or Feaver Spots, and ſuch like; but the <hi>Tokens</hi> are, I am confident, Marks ſent from God, and it is as impoſſible to cure any that once have them, as to contradict the Divine Decree; and beſides my own Family, many came to me both in my ſickneſs, and before and after, ſo that there was not a day during the Viſitation, but from Viſited houſes, and ſome that had running Sores, came daily to me, which I no more refuſed, then the ſoundeſt and healthieſt bodies, nor ſhall not God willing upon a juſt occaſion, nor to Viſit a Friend or Acquaintance in the greateſt of dangers, for I have ſeen many that have had many Sores and Blanes, ſome that have had the <hi>Tokens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe that had Riſings, I always adviſed them to annoint the Riſing with Oyl of Lillies, and Oyl of <hi>March</hi> Mallows, of each a like quantity; and if they broke, as ſome did, then to apply only that Oyntment, called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Apoſtolorum,</hi> and any Playſter, to keep the Lint that the Unguent was on to the Sore, and to take daily this Medicine inwardly, according as I ſhall afterward direct. So doing they have been perfectly cured by Gods aſſiſtance and this Medicine, and never troubled any Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon, though ſometimes there hath come forth a large Core.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103400:5"/>Neither is this Medicine only for this Diſeaſe, as the Authors men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and my own experience have found, for the greateſt part of my Practice hath been this many years, and it to this day, in thoſe Diſtempers which are by common Phyſitians accounted uncureable, and I have wrought and ſtill do no many other ingredients both Vegetables, Minerals, and Metals, and yet in all of them, I could never find neither ſo ſafe, nor ſo ſpeedily effectual a Medicine, as this one, which being of a Solar nature (that is cordial) that as the Sun by his Beams removes all Fogs and vapours from the earth, ſo this Medicine expells all venomous all obnoctious humours from the principle parts of the body, for it is ſo general a clenſer of the blood, that had I not ſeen the effects, I ſhould not have believed it, for I have applyed it both to perſons in Pleuriſies and Quincies, and in one hour the party hath been left perfectly at eaſe going to ſleep, and in their ſleep have been in a ſmall Sweat, and have waked well, not loſing one drop of blood, as the common cuſtom is.</p>
            <p>I have often cured a Feaver in two or three days; the ſmall Pox, which is a rotted putrid Feaver, I have cured in three days, the venom being breathed forth in a ſmall gentle ſweat, and the party perfectly well, and not any of the Small Pox hath ever come to matter, though they have been before much ſwell'd with them; the Hectick Feaver, which will not admit of bleeding without Death, is by this Medicine ſuddenly cured: The Convulſions I have frequently cured, even where there hath been no hopes of life, according to common reaſon; and I do my ſelf, and adviſe all my friends to give of it to their Children, firſt after they are born, ſix drops in a Spoonful of Ale; and I have had ſeveral that have given me thanks, and I always find the Child the better for it for a long time; and if the Mother of the Child take it ſo ſoon as ſhe is delivered, it will eaſe her of after pains, and prevent the vapours of the Mother, being taken for a few days night and morning in<note n="*" place="margin">Fear not the heat of the Sack for no Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will ever trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you if you take this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</note> Sack, faſting one hour after. I have had many Patients of the vapours, and been long in the curing of them, though I uſed the beſt means I could deviſe; but ſince I have made uſe of this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine for that ſad unquiet reſtleſs Diſtemper, I have found that a few dayes will cure it, except the party be old, and have had it many years, and then ſome longer time muſt be allowed, and by Gods bleſſing, you will not miſs your expected deſire. For the Palſey I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103400:6"/>have ſeveral times cured the worſt ſort of them, that is, the Palſey in both ſides; that in one ſide is but a trifle to the other, for in one there is but part of the Brain obſtructed, in the other it is all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed. The Swimming in the head, which is a forerunner of Melancholly, is preſently by this Medicine cured. Many are, by reaſon of bruiſes, troubled with Impoſtumations in the head, which, after having taken this Medicine, do caſt forth much corrupt matter by the Noſe, and after become well, and ſometimes the Hearing is obſtructed, and ſometimes the Sight grows dull by reaſon of a foul humour in the Brain, which I find is much helped by this Medicine; And although I have Spirit of Eye-bright in the houſe, and Eſſence of Sullandine, yet I prefer this Medicine before both, for the dimneſs of the Eyes, which I, by much working in the Fire and Mineral fumes cannot avoid the often receiving dammage both to the Eyes and Brain. That Diſeaſe called the <hi>Tremor,</hi> I have cured in Fourteen dayes, when the ſhaking was ſo violent, that if you held the hand ſtill, it would force the body to move; and one thing I am to inform thoſe that are Lovers of Children, when a Child in the month is froward, either by reaſon of ſome crudities it received from its Mothers overmuch eating of fruit, or from hurt or bruiſe in the birth,, or by reaſon of wind, then for ſome <hi>Diaſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium,</hi> ſaith the Nurſe; and that, ſaith ſhe, is a harmleſs thing, and will bring it to ſleep: and then the Mother preſently conſents, though it proves the Childs ruine, for though they do not give it ſo much, as contains ſo much Opium, as to cauſe it never to wake again, yet that little cold poyſon is the worſt of poyſons which will lodge in the body till it either brings the Convulſion fits, or, if the Child be ſo ſtrong of nature to paſs that danger, then after ſucceeds either the Rickets or Weakneſs in the Limbs. Which want of knowledge many after repent when it is too late. I had rather any Child of mine took Mercury, then half its weight in Opium, for I can ſpeak by experience of what I have ſeen in Children whom I have ſeen after they were born, and what they are brought to by this errour. There happens many times a windineſs in the <hi>Pleura,</hi> that is a skin within the Ribs near the Heart, which by delayes proves dangerous, alwayes coming with a difficulty of breathing, which is by this Medicine removed preſently, and by taking of it three or four dayes together, is fully cured; the windineſs of the Stomach is preſently expelled by it.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:103400:6"/>
            <p>The Scurvy, a Diſeaſe ſeldom taken notice of by people till their Teeth drop out, or a Dropſie followes them, or the Jaundies; and then what will they not do to be cured? They that have any of the three, or two of the, or all the three, let them take this Medicine and it will rid them of their grief: but obſerve always, the more the Diſeaſe is plycated, the longer is required for to continue the taking thereof. Always obſerve, fixt Diſeaſes require the longer for the removing, and are for the moſt part in leſs danger of death. The Spleen, cauſing either a pain in the ſide, of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſending up vapours into the head, cauſing unquiet ſleep, makes thoſe that are troubled therewith to be peeviſh, produces Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, it being the ſeat and receptacle of Melancholy. He or ſhe that takes this Medicine ſhall find a pain and tearing near the Spleen after an evacuation of much Wind downward, the Spleen being ſo near the Hypocondriacks, that ſeldom one is well and the other obſtructed, but commonly both together. I had a patient near ſix years agoe, that was in a deep Melancholy, that if he ſaw any one laugh would be very angry: alwayes he deſired this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, after he had once take of it, though he had others by: I have cured many Melancholy people, but by the taking this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine when the obſtructions opened, he broke ſo much wind back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that the neighbour at the next houſe wondred what noiſe that was; and after that, he was cured in a little time. That Diſeaſe the Seamen call the Belly-ake, which in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> kills ſo many brave men for want of help, had they with them but a ſmall Glaſs of this, they might be thereby preſerved, for it would quickly remove that intollerable pain, and ſend the cauſe forth at the back-dore. There is no Medicine in the world will ſute better with thoſe that go long Voyages to Sea, eſpecially into hot Counteys: for let them carry it to what part of the world they will, and keep the Glaſs cloſe ſtopped, it ſhall not loſe any thing of its virtues; for neither the heat of the Summer, nor coldeſt froſt that is, will take any more impreſſion on it then on a ſtone: That which will not preſerve it ſelf, cannot preſerve another. All ſorts of Fluxes is by this Medicine cured, ſometimes a Looſeneſs and Vomiting is cauſe by reaſon of Worms, which is always accompanyed with much Flegm: this Medicine breaks the bed of Worms, and leaves the Patient fully recovered, though few but have therewith a ſtrong
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103400:7"/>Feaver, which is cured alſo. There is a Diſeaſe which is called <hi>Lupus Phlegmaton,</hi> but by many fooliſhly taken for the Dropſie Tympanities, the Belly being ſwelled to a great bigneſs, by reaſon of congealed flegm. I have a Gentlewoman of near 50 years in this Diſtemper, and taking this Medicine three weeks or a month, found little alteration, but then did begin to be looſe, voiding much flegm; the next day ſhe vomited and was looſe, and the vomiting continued for two days, and every day came from her many Baſons full of flegm, and at the end ceaſed both vomiting and looſeneſs, having voided that which was the cauſe of her Diſtemper: during all the time of her Illneſs, ſhe ſtill continued taking this Medicine, and now happily rid of her Diſeaſe. This Medicine is both a great clenſer and ſtrengthener of the Spermatick Veſſels in men or women, thereby begetting fruitfulneſs in both Sexes; for it doth ſearch every corner of the body, and caſt forth what ever is offenſive to nature. The difficulty of making water doth ariſe from ſeveral cauſes, as from wind, from the ſtone, and from a ſlimy matter furring that paſſage of the Urine, and ſometimes by a carnoſity of the three firſt; I have had experience and find them eaſily helped by this Medicine: the Stone only deſires a long time for the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet I ſent ſome five years ago this Medicine to a Perſon of quality, and in Fourteen days after they ſent me word that it had ſo broken the ſtone, that there had come away two ſpoonfuls of Sand every day, for a long time. Now whether this was the Stone in the Kidneys or Bladder, I know not; for the Patient was a hundred Miles from me, but this I do not queſtion, but it will as well reach reach the Bladder as the Reins; for I once applyed it to a perſon that had an Ulcer in the neck of the Bladder, a man of near fifty years old, there was a tumor betwixt the Scrotum and the Fundament, the botch being broke before I knew it, ſo that the Urine came forth there every time he made water, and always in making water he had a great ſmarting in that place, after, as well as before the irregular paſſage of the Urine was ſtopped; yet I could find no Medicine that he found ſo much good by: but in ſhort time he was by this perfectly cured, without the leaſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in making water, although it brought away much mattery ſubſtance during the time any thing of corruption remained there. The ſymptoms by which you may know the Ulcer in the Bladder or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103400:7"/>the neck of the ſame, are pricking pain after making water in the end of the yard in men, and in woman in the paſſage of Urin: ſometimes there comes away a mattery ſubſtance with the Urin, ſometimes like hairs will appear in Urin, ſometimes both, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a ſmarting in making of water: and when there is nothing of the Venereal Diſeaſe, when theſe ſymptoms appear, then you may conclude there is an Ulcer either in the Bladder or in the Neck of the ſame: and in outward Ague-ſores, I have ſeen its effects, for being taken inwardly without ever applying any thing outwardly but a ſcorch'd rag, the ſores have run till the matter hath been fully taken away, and they have healed of their own accord: the Patient taking this Medicine daily till they were fully healed, after hath continued well many years, and I queſtion not but moſt ſores may be ſo healed, and the moſt venomeſt of Ulcers, Cancers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be made by the taking of it more apt to heal, for as they do proceed from a venomous humour, ſo this Medicine doth expel the greateſt of venoms: For when I have been by accident in Mineral fumes that will poyſon any man to continue in, I have taken no other Antidote againſt them. The Dropſie will fly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Medicine, for the Liver being freed from obſtructions and and the Urinary-paſſage, nature will do the reſt, unleſs it be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed with a Conſumption, and then there is but ſmall hopes of a cure. The Piles, a diſtemper much following Melancholy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and oftentimes that ſort called the blind Piles, which alwayes with a vehement pain and burning, as though fire was in the place, by the taking of this Medicine, it doth much mitigate the pain, and by degrees takes it fully away, but doth not fully ſtop the bleeding Piles, for that is the ſink of the body, and would be much injurious. Ruptures called Broken Bellies, which proceed from wind or water, this Medicine doth ſpeedily take away. A Rupture, is a wind in the lower Bowels cauſing an extention of the <hi>Peritonaeum,</hi> and in men and boys the Bowels extending the Kall, ſo that they fall into the <hi>Scrotum</hi> or Cod; and obſtructions of the Bowels being removed, the Diſtemper hath no place to lurk in. But what need I ſpend ſo much time and paper in mentioning particulars; ſince there is no Diſeaſe that I have met with, but this Medicine will cure: for I find that the obſtructions being opened, and the parts ſtrengthened, there can remain not any thing of a Diſeaſe in any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103400:8"/>part of the body.<note place="margin">I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven half a ſpoonful in peracute diſeaſes &amp; adviſe to giverather more than the doſe.</note> Now I ſhall direct how I always order the taking of it, my advice is to take it Night and Morning in a glaſs of Sack, and faſt one hour after, but not longer. The quantity to a ſtrong body, threeſcore drops, to a Child new born ſix drops, to one of a year old ten drops, of four years twenty, and to one of twelve years old forty; alwayes obſerving that ſome are as ſtrong at ſix years, as others at ten, and then the doſe is to be according. Thoſe that take it againſt Infections, need not take above twenty drops, and only in the morning, unleſs they go where infected people are, and then it is neceſſary to take it as often as they come where danger is. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it will be needful for thoſe that have the Infection, and have had it a day or two before they take it for them, then to take it four times a day, in the Morning, and at ten before noon, and at four after noon, and at night. Thoſe that are taken either with Pluriſie, Quinſie, or any other peracute Diſeaſe, let them take it ſo ſoon as the Diſeaſe appears, and if the firſt doſe doth not move it to their minds, then let them take it again two hours after, alwayes putting themſelves into bed ſo ſoon as they have taken it: and if they be dry, let them drink as much drink as they will in reaſon deſire; but always I forbid them ſmall beer: it being of a crude quality requires the more concoction, and ſo hinders the operation of the Medicine; but thoſe that are not lovers of ſtrong beer, let them mix Sack with their ſmall beer, and they will find that the leſs quantity of drink will allay their dryneſs. Now a word or two to my Brother <hi>Tyro,</hi> let me adviſe thee when thou goeſt about any chymical preparation, firſt to learn to know the three-fold Salt in nature, the three-fold Sulphur, and the three-fold Mercury; and the ſympathy and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy in them; their ſeperation and union, and the cauſe of their not uniting, the degrees of heat and cold required for their putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: underſtanding theſe, and then thou mayeſt be in hopes of accompliſhing ſome part of thy deſire; for if thou faileſt in any of them, thou wilt loſe thy labour.</p>
            <p>A word to thoſe that take this Medicine: before they take it, let them ſeriouſly conſider whether they can have patience in fix'd Diſeaſes, to continue the taking of it, as in old ſetled Griefs will be required, and if they cannot, I deſire them to let it alone; if they will take it, then let them in the firſt place deſire a bleſſing from God on it, and then queſtionleſs they ſhall obtain their deſire;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103400:8"/>and having obtained their deſire, let them return thanks to God for it; alwayes concluding they that receive any thing of good,<note place="margin">The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuſis is the beſt Schoolman in dyet.</note> and not giving thanks to God for it, do but rob God. For order in dyet, let the Patient eat what is moſt agreeable to the Stomach, alwayes obſerving that the Stomach better knows what will agree with it, then the Doctor doth, and let them ſone after the taking of it not walk abroad without eating, nor drink without eating. For per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume againſt Infectious airs, I always had Red Saunders and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of each a like quantity, and do approve it beſt, as the one comforting the Heart, the other the Brain.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="apothecarys_advertisement">
            <p>This Medicine truely prepared, that neither the heat of the Sun, nor the coldeſt froſt, nor age can hurt it, is to be had at this Authors Houſe, at the Sign of <hi>John Baptiſta Van Helmont</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Shadwell,</hi> near <hi>Ratcliff;</hi> at Mr. <hi>Gavel</hi>'s at the <hi>Falcon</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Playford</hi>'s in the <hi>Temple,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Brooke</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Greſham-Colledge</hi> towards <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Flemin</hi>'s at the <hi>Lamb</hi> in <hi>White-Chappel,</hi> near the <hi>Church,</hi> and at Mr. <hi>Conſtable</hi>'s a <hi>Potter</hi> in <hi>Montague-Cloſe</hi> in <hi>Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Each Glaſs contains either one Ounce, or Half an Ounce: the Price being 5 <hi>s.</hi> the Ounce, and 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> the Half.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
